I will draft an edict to depose the Crown Prince
짐이 조서를 내려 태자를 폐위하여
To satisfy them
불만을 잠재우도록 하지
All dismissed for now
모두 물러가거라
Let me have some peace
혼자 있고 싶다
Yes
예
Ruolan
약란
Fan Zhong
범충
Have Marquis of Yongning guard the empress's tomb
영녕후로 하여금 황후의 묘를 지키게 하라
Your Majesty
폐하
Your servant Xie Xuan requests an audience
신이 폐하를 뵙기를 청합니다
In the future, Great Xuan will be restored
훗날 선나라가 반드시 회복되고
Lost territories will be recovered
잃어버린 땅을 되찾는다면
In the history books
역사서에는
Not only brother-in-law
매형뿐만 아니라
Not only sister
누이뿐만 아니라
There will also be a record of me, Xie Xuan
저 사현의 이름 또한 한 줄 새겨질 것입니다
Fan Zhong
범충
Bring me a jug of wine
나를 위해 술 한 병만 가져다주게
The 21st year of Longwu
융무 21년
Xie Xuan was executed by Emperor Sikong Yao
사현은 황제 사공요에 의해
On charges of persecuting loyal officials
충신을 핍박했다는 죄목으로
In the capital
도성에서 참형에 처해졌습니다
At the same time
동시에 또다시 명을 내려
The Crown Prince
태자를 궁에 유폐시켰습니다
Time is up
시간이 되었다
Execute
형을 집행하라
Brother-in-law
매형
Speaking of defeat before the battle
싸우기도 전에 패배를 운운하다니
Staying in the capital has made your bones soft
도성에만 오래 있으니 겁쟁이가 된 거요?
Since we must fight to the death
사생결단할 거라면
I won't be such a coward
저도 겁쟁이로 있을 순 없습니다
Brother-in-law
매형
I request to lead the cavalry out of the city
제가 기병을 끌고 가겠습니다
You, as a Xuan person
선나라인으로서
Acting as a dog under the enemy's tent
적 밑에서 개노릇 하며
Xie Xuan, deputy general of Yiyang garrison
익양성 수비군 부장 사현
Kill him
저놈은 죽이고요
One day
하루
Give me one more day
하루만 더 주세요
I will personally lead the battle
제가 직접 진두지휘해서
Under my command
저한테도
There are also over a hundred men
백여 명이 있습니다
To clear the way for Your Highness
전하를 위해 길을 열어라!
General Zu
조 장군
Please rise quickly
어서 일어나시오
You've worked hard, General Zu
고생 많았소, 조 장군
I will reward you heavily
짐이 크게 상을 내리겠네
Read
읽거라
General of Agile Cavalry Zu Yue
표기장군 조월은
Loyalty and courage bestowed by heaven
충의와 용맹이 뛰어나고
Meritorious achievements are clear
공적이 혁혁하다
Rescued the emperor and quelled rebellion
황실을 위해 난을 평정함에 있어
Merits surpass all officials
그 공이 누구보다도 크니
Now
특별히 대장군에 책봉한다
Envoy with credentials, bearer of yellow battle-axe
황제 전권을 대행해 즉결 처분을 허락하며
Commander of all military affairs
나라 안팎의 모든 군대를 통솔하고
Granted the nine bestowments and special honors
공신 최고의 예우인 구석을 하사한다
May enter court without hurrying
조정에서의 격식을 면하고
Addressed without name
이름 대신 관직으로 불리고
May enter court with sword and shoes
칼을 차고 조당에 들 수 있다
Opened a government office equal to the Three Excellencies
거기에 개부의동삼사의 예우를 더한다
Your servant Zu Yue
신 조월은
Kowtows in gratitude for the imperial grace
성은에 머리 숙여 감사드립니다